你好，黑客们，欢迎来到pwn大学，我是Yan
hello hackers welcome to pwn college I'm Yan
在这个视频中，我们将讨论
and in this video we're going to be talking about
内存错误
memory errors
特别是一种非常简单的内存错误
specifically a very simple type of memory error
经典的栈溢出
kind of the the classic stack overflow
嗯，我们要谈谈针对栈的攻击
um we're gonna talk about smashing the stack
让我们从一个简单的例子开始
let's start with a simple example
就是本次视频中的例子
this will be the example of the video
如果你有一个程序，这个程序从用户
let's see if you have a program and the program takes input from the user
通过命令行获得命令行参数作为输入
on the command line as a command line argument
就在这里
that's right here right
然后把它传递给这个print_quoted函数
and it passes it into this print quoted function
该函数打印出一个带引号的字符串
and the print quoted function prints out a quoted version of the string
字符串的引号版本长什么样？
what does the quoted version of the string look like
这个quote函数
we have this quote function
它有一个输出缓冲区
that has an output buffer and
它用sprintf将引号括起来的字符串填充到输出缓冲区
it uses sprintf to fill the output buffer with a version of the string that we passed in surrounded by quotes
这个程序有许多bug
this program has a number of bugs in it
在这个视频里，将讨论程序中出现的栈溢出
and in this video we're going to talk about the stack overflow that's present in this program
栈溢出发生在这个sprintf中
and the stack overflow occurs in this sprintf
这个sprintf是不安全的
this sprintf is unsafe
它无法知道缓冲区有多大
it has no way of understanding how big the buffer is
所以问题就来了
and so there are problems
用户输入是不受限制的
and of course the user input is not limited
让我们看看当恶意用户
so let's see what happens when a malicious user
将一个很长的字符串传给参数1
passes in a very long argument into argue 1, a very long string
会发生什么
what happens of course
当sprintf运行时
when sprintf runs
它在栈上分配了一些空间
it allocates some space on the stack
创建它的元数据或它需要的任何局部变量
creates its metadata or whatever local data that it needs to have
当它启动时
and when it launches
栈上有函数返回地址
there's this return address that is pushed
返回地址表示，当sprintf返回后
and the return address says when you return from sprintf
回到代码的第14行。当然，我们看的是源代码
go to this line 14 in the code of course we're looking at source code
实际上是二进制的
in reality this will be binary
然后sprintf写入一个引号
then sprintf writes one quote
然后是输入
then the input
然后另一个引号到栈上
and then another quote onto the stack
写到输出缓冲区所在的位置
onto specifically where this output buffer was
quote函数栈帧中的输出缓冲区
an output buffer was in the stack frame of the quote function
当输出缓冲区填满时
and when the output buffers filled
因为对命令行参数的大小没有限制
because there is no limit on the size of a command line argument
实际上是有，但是是65kb
or I mean there is but it's like 65 KB
但整个输出缓冲区只用16字节就被填满了
there the entire output buffer which was only 16 bytes long is completely filled up
如果你注意到
and if you notice
当您将output传给sprintf时
when you passing this output into sprintf
它所需要的只是一个字符指针
all that it takes is a character pointer
让我们在命令行里看看
let's take a look on the command line here
man sprintf
因为printf只接收一个字符指针
as printf takes a character pointer
所以对于它的输出缓冲区
and for its output buffer
它没有办法知道缓冲区的大小
it has no way of knowing the size of that character of buffer
所以如果没有额外的信息提供给它，它就别无选择
and so it has no choice without any additional information provided to it
当然，在一个完善的程序中，你可以这样做
and of course in a well formed program you could
例如，在这里设置一个大小限制
put a size limit here for example
或者你可以用一个更安全的函数
or you could use a more safe function
比如snprintf
such as snprintf
它别无选择，只能复制整个字符串
it has no choice but to copy the whole string
当然，如果整个字符串太长
and of course if the whole string is too long
它会溢出
it'll overflow
这里是什么
and what was over here
这里是返回地址，它决定
over here used to be the return address from quote which said
当quote返回时，转到源代码print_quoted的第9行
when quote returns go to line 9 in the source code in print quote
或者任何与之对应的二进制指令
or whatever binary instruction corresponded to that
结果是
so what happens is
攻击者的输入会覆盖缓冲区里和后的所有内容
the attacker input overwrites everything over the buffer
然后覆盖返回地址
and writes over that return address
然后当返回地址
then when that return address
当函数返回时
when the return from the function happens
会有不好的结果
there are bad effects so
所以这里出了什么问题？
what went wrong here right
有两处出了问题。一种是懒惰的编程习惯
two things went wrong. one is a kind of lazy programming practice
很容易搞砸对sprintf的调用
it's very easy to screw up a call to sprintf
因为你的栈溢出了，不好的事情会发生
and cause your stacks who get overflowed and bad things happen
但还有一个更微妙的问题
but there's a more subtle problem
在这个程序中更微妙的问题是
the more subtle problem is in this program
指向大小可变数据结构的指针被传参时
there were pointers being passed around to variable size data structures
数据结构的大小没有被一起传
without the size also being passed around
如果不是字符数组
if instead of a character array
如果不是output字符指针
instead of a character pointer of output
被单独传入，没有大小信息
being passed in alone with no size information
而是
if instead
这个程序使用了类似snprintf的函数
the program used something like snprintf
让我们再看一下我们的手册
let's take a look at our man pages again
Snprintf接受字符指针
snprintf takes the character pointer
字符缓冲区指针并且还有大小
the character buffer pointer and a size right
如果使用了这个，大小被传递进来
if this was used and the size was passed in
这个bug是可以避免的
this bug could have been avoided
不幸的是，通常在C语言中
unfortunately oftentimes in C
因为没有任何隐式元数据
because there is no implicit metadata to anything
在代码中会看到很多这类导致缓冲区溢出的内存错误
you see a lot of these sorts of memory errors leading to buffer overflows in real code
可以利用这种内存损坏做什么？
what can you do with this memory corruption
自问一下
right let's ask this for yourself
你可以做很多的事情
well you can do a lot of stuff right
当然可以
you could of course
覆盖不影响任何事情的内存
overwrite memory that doesn't influence anything
栈上有很多用来对齐的填充内存
there's plenty of memory uh padding on the stack etc
这很无聊，对吧
that's boring right
但还有一些更有趣的
but then there are a couple of more interesting
可以用栈溢出做的一些像大家讨论的那种事情
things that you can do with a stack overflow like they're discussing right
可以覆盖堆栈上的其他内存
you could overwrite some other memory on the stack
例如在同一个函数中的其他局部变量
other local variables for example in that same function
用来影响一些数学运算
that are used to influence some mathematical operations
一些条件跳转等等
some conditional jumps etc right
你可能还记得那场胜利
you might remember the win
我猜你们还没看到
well I guess you wouldn't have seen that yet
在你的本模块的挑战问题
in your the the challenge problems for this module
你会看到这些你可以覆盖和影响的变量
you'll see these sort of variables that you can overwrite  and influence
您还可以覆盖一些
you could also overwrite some memory
用作读指针或读指针偏移量的内存
that is used as a read pointer or an offset of a read pointer
这样你就可以让程序
that will allow you to forge the program
去访问一些本不会访问的内存
to access some memory that wasn't supposed to right
对于写指针也可以这样做
you can do the same for a write pointer
导致所谓的任意内存覆盖漏洞
allowing for what is called an arbitrary write um memory overwrite vulnerability
你可以用类似但更直接的方法
and you can use something similar but even more brutal
就是覆盖代码指针
which is overriding a code pointer
稍后程序将用于更改控制流的指针
a pointer that the program will later used to transfer control flow
比如说
um for example
我们在这里看到的返回地址
the return address that we saw being over within
这个例子叫做控制流劫持漏洞利用
the example this is um called a control flow hijack exploit
嗯嗯
uh and um
这是一种非常非常强大的利用方式
it's a very very powerful type of exploit
因为你控制了程序
because you take control of the program
嗯通常
um typically
当然，你也可以实现多个这样的效果
of course you might be able to do multiples of these effects
通过多次触发相同的bug
by either triggering the same bug multiple times
或者按顺序覆盖多个不同的东西
or the overwriting multiple different things that are used in sequence for example
当然终极力量
but of course the ultimate power
我们将重点关注的
and what we'll focus on
尤其是在后面的作业中
and especially the later parts of the homework
是覆盖返回指针
is return pointer overriding
溢出栈缓冲区以覆盖返回指针
you overflow a stack buffer to override the return pointers
现在有各种各样的补救方式
and there's all sorts of complications and
在很多很多情况下，这种利用已经过时了
and in in many many cases this is now obsolete
这一模块中我们会讲到
but we'll roll into that in this module
你还可以做其他有趣的事情
um other things you could do that are very interesting
你在返回地址覆盖时不仅可以跳转到其它函数
you can jump not just to a different function in your return point overwrite
还可以跳转到任何指令
you can jump to any instruction
这是一个非常强大的能力
this is a very powerful capability
你可以将功能链式组装起来
and you can actually chain functionality
你会深入了解这方面
you'll dive into this
在下一模块会对这方面非常深入
you have extreme depth in the next module
在面向返回编程模块中
actually in return oriented programming
你也可以在指令之间切换
and you can jump between instructions as well
这也是一种非常有趣的能力
this is also a very interesting sort of capability
特别是在x86和AMD64上
especially on x86 and AMD64
我们将在下一模块中探讨这三个概念
and we'll explore these three concepts in the next module
但是现在让我们回到我们的例子
but for now let's look back at our example
并考虑
and consider
覆盖返回地址以指向其他函数
overwriting the return address to point to some other function
这里是我们的攻击点
and specifically here we have our attack
在这里我们覆盖返回地址
where we override the return address
我们可以用我们控制的返回地址覆盖它
we could override it with a return address that we control
特别是如果有一个win函数之类的
and specifically if there's for example a win function or whatever
执行任意命令的函数，是一个非常理想的目标
a function that execute arbitrary commands  that is a very desirable function
要跳转到代码，我们可以用目标地址覆盖返回地址
to jump to the code we can override the return address with the location of that function
当quote返回时，将执行我们想要执行的函数
and then when quote returns we will execute the function that we want to execute
快速地看一下在实际中是如何工作的
let's take a quick look at the terminal how this actually works in practice
首先让我们在 Binary Ninja上看看
actually 1st let's look on binary ninja
我编译了这个程序
so I compiled this program
这里是main，它调用了print_quoted
here is main which of course calls print quoted
print_quoted调用quote
print quoted calls quote
quote调用sprintf，然后返回
quote calls sprintf and then returns
好的，来到终端，我们用GDB调试它
all right let's jump to the terminal and we will GDB this
这是加载了插件的GDB
so this is GDB with split mind and stuff
你可以自己配置环境
you can of course set it up
或者使用PWN学院的环境
or use the pwn college infrastructure which has this available to you
这种预先设置
kind of preset up
在quote函数下断点
so let's break at the quote function
然后用一个正常的
and then run with a normal
正常的，正常的什么
normal what's it called normal
额，输入，不好意思我愣了一下
input sorry on my mind went blank
我们在quote处中断
so we broke out quote
你可以在栈上看到
and you can see on the stack here
实际上，让我们跳过栈的建立
actually let's let's step through the stack setup
好了
okay
现在我们已经设置好栈了
now we should have the stack all set up
如果我们看RSP
if we look at RSP
在RSP或者栈上中还没有任何东西
we have nothing in RSP yet or nothing on on our stack
这里应该是我们写入引号输入的地方
this should be where we write the quoted version of our input
如果我没记错，是第一个参数hello
which was if I remember correctly hello as the 1st argument
如果我们继续下一个指令
so if we go next instruction
现在我们将要执行sprintf
now we're about to execute sprintf
使用quote % s quote的格式字符串
with a format string of quote percent s quote
和参数：hello
and argument hello
好了
all right
这是之前的堆栈缓冲区
here is our stack buffer before
什么鬼
what the heck
跑哪里去了
are we where are we are now
这应该是对的
I should this should be right
为什么呢?
why is that it
哦，它可能不在(栈)的顶部
oh well it might just not be at the top of the (stack)
所以看起来在RDI
so seemingly it is at RDI
好吧
okay
这是我们的hello
so here's our hello
出于某种原因它在RSP+10，可能有填充或扩展
alright it is RSP plus 10 for some reason maybe there was padding or extend
这是我们的字符串hello
so here's our string hello
加了引号，很好，如果我们看
right quoted nicely and if we look at
如果我们执行下一条指令
if we go to next instruction
我们马上就要返回了
we're about to return
现在在c28
here is at C 28
距离hello 0x18
so hex 1 8 away from hello
是我们的返回地址
is the return address that we're about to return to
你可以在这里的调用栈中看到
you can see this back trace right here
所以我们要从quote回到print_quoted
so we're about to go from quote to print quoted
我们已经回到print_quoted，我们可以继续
and we're back in print quoted and we can continue
看起来哪里出了问题
onwards it looks like something is broken
我们看不到输出
and we don't see the output
这没关系
that's okay all right so
这就是该程序正常的工作方式
that's basically how the program supposed to work but
让我们看看当恶意攻击者——我们自己
let's see what happens when a malicious attacker ourselves
发送一个很长的字符串会发生什么
instead sends a very long string
好，现在我们回到quote
okay so now we're back at quote
我们到了
here we are
先跳到调用sprintf
let's just step through until we call sprintf
好了，开始吧
okay so here we go
我们将调用sprintf
we're about to call sprintf
用缓冲区地址
with our buffer address
用"%s"格式字符串
with the quote percent s quote format
和非常大的字符串
and with our very large string now
让我们快速看一下
so let's take a look real quick
首先，这是缓冲区如果我们看到RSP在哪里
1st here's this buffer right so if we see where RSP is
这是RSP
this is RSP
这就是我们要写东西的地方
this is where we're going to write stuff
从bb0到bc0
so we go from bb0 to bc0
和之前一样，到返回地址的距离是0x10
so as before we were 0x10 away and where is our return address
返回地址在RBP + 8
our return address um resides at RBP plus 8
如果你还记得我们对栈的讨论
so if you recall our discussion of the stack
RBP指向栈的右边，也就是返回地址的前面
RBP points to the right side of the stack the kind of where right before the return address
RBP + 8，(rbp)再右边一个就是返回值
RBP plus 8 just one further right that is the return value
这当然指向这里的print_quoted+28
and that of course points us to print quoted plus 28 here
我们将返回到print_quoted
we'll return back into print quoted
好的
all right
执行下一步
if we step over this
你将会看到一些变化
you're about to see a couple of things changed
最直接的是这个调用栈
the immediate thing is gonna be this back trace
会完全乱掉
will go completely nuts
因为整个
because the entire
额，不是整个栈，而是栈上的一部分
well not the entire stack but a whole lot of the stack
被A十六进制ASCII值41覆盖
was overwritten with A  which is in ASCII hex 41
如果看一下现在的结果
so if you look at their turnout just now
是十六进制41
it's hex 41
这是个坏消息，因为如果我们继续前进
that's pretty bad news because if we keep stepping
现在我们到了leave指令
so now we're stepping to the stack clean up
执行返回，然后崩溃了
we're stepping through the return and we crash
为什么我们会崩溃
why do we crash
因为我们会尝试返回
because we try to return of course
Return将返回地址从堆栈中取出并跳转到那里
return pops the return address off the stack and goes there
返回地址都是A
and the return address is all A's
这是个坏消息
so that's pretty bad news
显然访问0x41414141 41414141，程序会崩溃
obviously for all A's the program just crashes
但是如果我们有一个win函数
but if we had a win function
我们可以精心设计我们的输入
we could carefully craft our input
它包含的不是全A而是win函数的地址
so that instead of all A's it contained the address of the win function
太棒了
awesome
这是最简单的堆栈溢出的例子
so this is the kind of the simplest stack overflow example
或者不是最简单的，但你知道一个简单的
or not quite the simplest but you know a simple one
在本模块的其余部分，我们将讨论其他可能发生的内存错误
in the rest of the module we'll go into other memory errors that can occur
然后是为了防止利用而采取的缓解措施
and then the mitigations that are supposed to protect against their exploitation
感谢收看
thanks for watching